<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="windows-installation" type="original" xml:base="windows-installation/windows-installation.xml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Setting Up an Integrated Development Environment for Python (Windows)</title>
                <author role="original_author">
                    <persName>William J. Turkel</persName>
                    <persName>Adam Crymble</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="reviewers">
                    <persName>Jim Clifford</persName>
                    <persName>Amanda Morton</persName>
                </editor>
                <editor role="editors">Miriam Posner</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>Programming Historian</distributor>
                <idno type="doi">10.46430/phen0019</idno>
                <date type="published">07/17/2012</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital, in a markdown format. This lesson is original. Available translations are the following:<ref type="translations" target="#instalacao-windows #instalacion-windows #installation-windows-py"/>
                </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p>This lesson will help you set up an integrated development environment for Python on a computer running the Windows operating system.</p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term xml:lang="en">get-ready</term>
                    <term xml:lang="en">python</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div type="2" n="1">
                <head>Back up your computer</head>
                <p>It is always important to make sure you have regular and recent backups
of your computer. This is just good advice for life, and is not limited
to times when you are engaged in programming.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="2" n="2">
                <head>Install Python v.3</head>
                <p>Go to the <ref target="http://www.python.org/">Python website</ref>, download the latest stable release of the
Python programming language (Version 3.8 as of November 2019) and install
it by following the instructions on the Python website.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="2" n="3">
                <head>Create a Directory</head>
                <p>To stay organized, it’s best to have a dedicated directory (folder) on
your computer where you will keep your Python programs (e.g.,
<code rend="inline">programming-historian</code>) and save it anywhere you like on your hard
drive.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="2" n="4">
                <head>Install Komodo Edit</head>
                <p>Komodo Edit is a free and open source code editor, but you have many
<ref target="http://wiki.python.org/moin/PythonEditors/">other text editing options</ref> if you want to use another programme. You can
download a copy from the <ref target="http://www.activestate.com/komodo-edit">Komodo Edit website</ref>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="2" n="5">
                <head>Start Komodo Edit</head>
                <p>It should look something like this:</p>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Komodo Edit on Windows</desc>
                    <graphic url="komodo-edit11-windows-main.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>If you don’t see the Toolbox pane on the right hand side, choose
<code rend="inline">View -&gt; Tabs -&gt; Toolbox</code>. It doesn’t matter if the Project pane is open
or not. Take some time to familiarize yourself with the layout of the
Komodo editor. The Help file is quite good.</p>
                <div type="3" n="5.1">
                    <head>Configure Komodo Edit</head>
                    <p>Now you need to set up the editor so that you can run Python programs.</p>
                    <p>Choose <code rend="inline">Edit -&gt; Preferences -&gt; Languages -&gt; Python 3</code> and then select <code rend="inline">Browse</code>. Now select    <code rend="inline">C:\Users\YourUserName\AppData\Local\Programs\Python\Python38-32</code>)
If it looks like this, click OK:</p>
                    <p>{% include figure.html caption="Set the Default Python Interpreter
" filename="komodo-edit11-windows-interpreter.png" %}</p>
                    <p>Next, in the Preferences section select <emph>Internationalization</emph>.
Select <emph>Python</emph> from the drop-down menu titled <emph>Language-specific
Default Encoding</emph> and make sure that <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UTF-8">UTF-8</ref> is selected as the
default encoding method.</p>
                    <p>{% include figure.html caption="Set the Language to UTF-8" filename="komodo-edit11-windows-utf-set.png" %}</p>
                    <p>Next choose <code rend="inline">Toolbox-&gt;Add-&gt;New Command</code>. This will open a new dialog
window. Rename your command to <code rend="inline">‘Run Python’</code>. Under <code rend="inline">‘Command’</code>, type:</p>
                    <ab>
                        <code lang="language-python" xml:id="code_windows-installation_0" corresp="code_windows-installation_0.txt" rend="block"/>
                    </ab>
                    <p>If you forget this command, Python will hang mysteriously because it
isn't receiving a program as input.</p>
                    <p>Under <code rend="inline">‘Start in’</code>, enter:</p>
                    <p>
                        <code rend="inline">%D</code>
                    </p>
                    <p>If it looks like this, click OK:</p>
                    <figure>
                        <desc>'Run Python' Command</desc>
                        <graphic url="komodo-edit11-windows-python-command.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <figure>
                        <desc>Configuring the command 'Run Python Start'.</desc>
                        <graphic url="komodo-edit11-windows-python-start.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Your new command should appear in the Toolbox pane. You may need to
restart your machine after completing this step before Python will work
with Komodo Edit.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="2" n="6">
                <head>Step 2 – 'Hello World' in Python</head>
                <p>It is traditional to begin programming in a new language by trying to
create a program that says 'hello world' and terminates. We will show
you how to do this in Python and HTML.</p>
                <p>Python is a good programming language for beginners because it is very
high-level. It is possible, in other words, to write short programs that
accomplish a lot. The shorter the program, the more likely it is for the
whole thing to fit on one screen, and the easier it is to keep track of
all of it in your mind.</p>
                <p>Python is an 'interpreted' programming language. This means that
there is a special computer program (known as an interpreter) that knows
how to follow instructions written in that language. One way to use the
interpreter is to store all of your instructions in a file, and then run
the interpreter on the file. A file that contains programming language
instructions is known as a program. The interpreter will execute each of
the instructions that you gave it in your program and then stop. Let’s
try this.</p>
                <p>In your text editor, create a new file, enter the following two-line
program and save it to your <code rend="inline">programming-historian</code> directory as
<code rend="inline">hello-world.py</code>
                </p>
                <ab>
                    <code lang="language-python" xml:id="code_windows-installation_1" corresp="code_windows-installation_1.txt" rend="block"/>
                </ab>
                <p>Your chosen text editor should have a “<code rend="inline">Run</code>” button that will allow you
to execute your program. If all went well, it should look something like
this (Example as seen in Komodo Edit. Click on the image to see a
full-size copy):</p>
                <figure>
                    <desc>'Hello World'</desc>
                    <graphic url="komodo-edit11-windows-hello.png"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="2" n="7">
                <head>Interacting with a Python shell</head>
                <p>Another way to interact with an interpreter is to use what is known as a
shell. You can type in a statement and press the Enter key, and the
shell will respond to your command. Using a shell is a great way to test
statements to make sure that they do what you think they should.</p>
                <p>You can run a Python Shell by double-clicking on the python.exe file. If
you installed version 3.8 (the most recent as of November 2019), then this
file is probably located in the <code rend="inline">C:\Users\YourUserName\AppData\Local\Programs\Python\Python38-32</code> directory. In
the shell window that opens on your screen type:</p>
                <ab>
                    <code lang="language-python" xml:id="code_windows-installation_2" corresp="code_windows-installation_2.txt" rend="block"/>
                </ab>
                <p>and press Enter. The computer will respond with</p>
                <ab>
                    <code lang="language-python" xml:id="code_windows-installation_3" corresp="code_windows-installation_3.txt" rend="block"/>
                </ab>
                <p>When we want to represent an interaction with the shell, we will use -&gt;
to indicate the shell’s response to your command, as shown below:</p>
                <ab>
                    <code lang="language-python" xml:id="code_windows-installation_4" corresp="code_windows-installation_4.txt" rend="block"/>
                </ab>
                <p>On your screen, it will look more like this:</p>
                <p>{% include figure.html caption="Python Shell in Windows" filename="windows-python3-cmd.png" %}</p>
                <p>Now that you and your computer are up and running, we can move onto some
more interesting tasks. If you are working through the Python lessons in
order, we suggest you next try ‘<ref target="/lessons/viewing-html-files">Understanding Web Pages and HTML</ref>‘</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
