<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="working-with-web-pages">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Downloading Web Pages with Python</title>
                <author role="original_author">
                    <persName>William J. Turkel</persName>
                    <persName>Adam Crymble</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="reviewers">
                    <persName>Jim Clifford</persName>
                    <persName>Frederik Elwert</persName>
                </editor>
                <editor role="editors">Miriam Posner</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>Programming Historian</distributor>
                <idno type="doi">10.46430/phen0021</idno>
                <date type="published">07/17/2012</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital, in a markdown format. This lesson is original. Available translations are the following:<ref type="translations" target="#download-paginas-web-python #telecharger-des-pages-web-avec-python #trabajar-con-paginas-web"/>
                </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p>This lesson introduces Uniform Resource Locators (URLs) and explains how to use Python to download and save the contents of a web page to your local hard drive.</p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term xml:lang="en">python</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div type="2">
                <head>Lesson Goals</head>
                <p>This lesson introduces <emph>Uniform Resource Locators</emph> (URLs) and explains how
to use Python to download and save the contents of a web page to your
local hard drive.</p>
                <div type="3">
                    <head>About URLs</head>
                    <p>A <emph>web page</emph> is a file that is stored on another computer, a machine known
as a <emph>web server</emph>. When you "go to" a web page, what is actually happening
is that your computer, (the <emph>client</emph>) sends a request to the server (the
<emph>host</emph>) out over the network, and the server replies by sending a copy of
the page back to your machine. One way to get to a web page with your
browser is to follow a link from somewhere else. You also have the
ability, of course, to paste or type a Uniform Resource Locator (URL)
directly into your browser. The URL tells your browser where to find an
online resource by specifying the server, directory and name of the file
to be retrieved, as well as the kind of <emph>protocol</emph> that the server and
your browser will agree to use while exchanging information (like HTTP,
the <emph>Hypertext Transfer Protocol</emph>). The basic structure of a URL is</p>
                    <ab>
                        <code xml:id="code_working-with-web-pages_0" corresp="code_working-with-web-pages_0.txt" rend="block"/>
                    </ab>
                    <p>Let's look at a few examples.</p>
                    <ab>
                        <code lang="language-xml" xml:id="code_working-with-web-pages_1" corresp="code_working-with-web-pages_1.txt" rend="block"/>
                    </ab>
                    <p>The most basic kind of URL simply specifies the protocol and host. If
you give this URL to your browser, it will return the main page of The
<ref target="http://www.oldbaileyonline.org/">Old Bailey Online</ref> website. The default assumption is that the main
page in a given directory will be named index, usually <code rend="inline">index.html</code>.</p>
                    <p>The URL can also include an optional <emph>port number</emph>. Without getting into
too much detail, the network protocol that underlies the
exchange of information on the Internet allows computers to connect in
different ways. Port numbers are used to distinguish these different
kinds of connection. Since the default port for HTTP is 80, the
following URL is equivalent to the previous one.</p>
                    <ab>
                        <code lang="language-xml" xml:id="code_working-with-web-pages_2" corresp="code_working-with-web-pages_2.txt" rend="block"/>
                    </ab>
                    <p>As you know, there are usually many web pages on a given website. These
are stored in directories on the server, and you can specify the path to
a particular page. The "About" page for <emph>The Old Bailey Online</emph> has the
following URL.</p>
                    <ab>
                        <code lang="language-xml" xml:id="code_working-with-web-pages_3" corresp="code_working-with-web-pages_3.txt" rend="block"/>
                    </ab>
                    <p>Finally, some web pages allow you to enter queries. <emph>The Old Bailey
Online</emph> website, for example, is laid out in such a way that you can
request a particular page within it by using a <emph>query string</emph>. The
following URL will take you to a search results page for criminal record
trials containing the word "arsenic".</p>
                    <ab>
                        <code lang="language-xml" xml:id="code_working-with-web-pages_4" corresp="code_working-with-web-pages_4.txt" rend="block"/>
                    </ab>
                    <p>The snippet after the "?" represents the query. You can learn more about
building queries in <ref target="/lessons/downloading-multiple-records-using-query-strings">Downloading Multiple Records Using Query
Strings</ref>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="2">
                <head>Opening URLs with Python</head>
                <p>As a digital historian you will often find yourself wanting to use data
held in scholarly databases online. To get this data you could open URLs
one at a time and copy and paste their contents to a text file, or you
can use Python to automatically harvest and process webpages. To do
this, you're going to need to be able to open URLs with your own
programs. The Python language includes a number of standard ways to do
this.</p>
                <p>As an example, let's work with the kind of file that you might encounter
while doing historical research. Say you're interested in race relations
in eighteenth century Britain. 'The Old Bailey Online' (OBO) is a rich resource that provides trial transcripts from
1674 to 1913 and is one good place to seek sources.</p>
                <figure>
                    <desc>The Old Bailey Online Homepage</desc>
                    <graphic url="old-bailey.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>For this example, we will be using the trial transcript of Benjamin
Bowsey, a “black moor” who was convicted of breaking the peace during
the <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gordon_Riots">Gordon Riots</ref> of 1780. The URL for the entry is</p>
                <ab>
                    <code lang="language-xml" xml:id="code_working-with-web-pages_5" corresp="code_working-with-web-pages_5.txt" rend="block"/>
                </ab>
                <p>By studying the URL we can learn a few things. First, The OBO is written
in JSP (<emph>JavaServer Pages</emph>, a web programming language which outputs
HTML), and it’s possible to retrieve individual trial entries by making
use of the query string. Each is apparently given a unique ID number
(<emph>id=t</emph> in the URL), built from the date of the trial session in the
format (<emph>YYYYMMDD</emph>) and the trial number from within that court session,
in this case: <emph>33</emph>. If you change the two instances of <code rend="inline">33</code> to <code rend="inline">34</code> in
your browser and press Enter, you should be taken to the next trial.
Unfortunately, not all websites have such readable and reliable URLs.</p>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Trial Transcript Page of Benjamin Bowsey, 1780</desc>
                    <graphic url="bowsey-trial-page.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Spend a few minutes looking at Benjamin Bowsey’s trial page. Here we are
not so much interested in what the transcript says, but what features
the page has. Notice the <ref target="http://www.oldbaileyonline.org/browse.jsp?foo=bar&amp;path=sessionsPapers/17800628.xml&amp;div=t17800628-33&amp;xml=yes">View as XML</ref> link at the bottom that takes
you to a heavily marked up version of the text which may be useful to
certain types of research. You can also look at a <ref target="http://www.oldbaileyonline.org/images.jsp?doc=178006280084">scan of the original
document</ref>, which was transcribed to make this resource.</p>
                <p>Now let's try opening the page using Python. Copy the following program
into Komodo Edit and save it as <code rend="inline">open-webpage.py</code>. When you execute the
program, it will <code rend="inline">open</code> the trial file, <code rend="inline">read</code> its contents into a Python
string called webContent and then <code rend="inline">print</code> the first three hundred
characters of the string to the "Command Output" pane. Use the
<code rend="inline">View -&gt; Web Developer -&gt; View Page Source</code> command in Firefox to verify
that the HTML source of the page is the same as the source that your
program retrieved. Each browser has a different shortcut key to open the
page source. In Firefox on PC it is <code rend="inline">CTRL+u</code>. If you cannot find it on
your browser, try using a search engine to find where it is. (See the
Python library reference to learn more about <ref target="https://docs.python.org/3/library/urllib.html?highlight=urllib">urllib</ref>.)</p>
                <ab>
                    <code lang="language-python" xml:id="code_working-with-web-pages_6" corresp="code_working-with-web-pages_6.txt" rend="block"/>
                </ab>
                <p>These five lines of code achieve an awful lot very quickly. Let us take
a moment to make sure that everything is clear and that you can
recognize the building blocks that allow us to make this program do what
we want it to do.</p>
                <p>
                    <emph>url</emph>, <emph>response</emph>, and <emph>webContent</emph> are all variables that we have named
ourselves.</p>
                <p>
                    <emph>url</emph> holds the URL of the web page that we want to download. In this
case, it is the trial of Benjamin Bowsey.</p>
                <p>On the following line, we call the function <code rend="inline">urlopen</code>, which is stored in
a Python module named <code rend="inline">urllib.py</code>, and we have asked that function to
open the website found at the URL we just specified. We then saved the
result of that process into a variable named <emph>response</emph>. That variable now
contains an open version of the requested website.</p>
                <p>We then use the <code rend="inline">read</code> method, which we used earlier, to copy the contents
of that open webpage into a new variable named <emph>webContent</emph>.</p>
                <p>Make sure you can pick out the variables (there are 3 of them), the
modules (1), the methods (2), and the parameters (1) before you move on.</p>
                <p>In the resulting output, you will notice a little bit of HTML markup:</p>
                <ab>
                    <code lang="language-xml" xml:id="code_working-with-web-pages_7" corresp="code_working-with-web-pages_7.txt" rend="block"/>
                </ab>
                <p>The content of the trial itself is much further down the page. What we
see here is the HTML code at the top of the document. This is not quite
what we need for historical research, but don't worry; you
will soon learn how to remove that excess markup and get the content you are after.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="2">
                <head>Saving a Local Copy of a Web Page</head>
                <p>Given what you already know about writing to files, it is quite easy to
modify the above program so that it writes the contents of the
<emph>webContent</emph> string to a local file on our computer rather than to the
"Command Output" pane. Copy the following program into Komodo Edit, save
it as <code rend="inline">save-webpage.py</code> and execute it. Using the <code rend="inline">File -&gt; Open File</code>
command in Firefox, open the file on your hard drive that it creates
(<code rend="inline">obo-t17800628-33.html</code>) to confirm that your saved copy is the same as
the online copy.</p>
                <ab>
                    <code lang="language-python" xml:id="code_working-with-web-pages_8" corresp="code_working-with-web-pages_8.txt" rend="block"/>
                </ab>
                <p>So, if you can save a single file this easily, could you write a program
to download a bunch of files? Could you step through trial IDs, for
example, and make your own copies of a whole bunch of them? Yep. You can learn
how to do that in <ref target="/lessons/downloading-multiple-records-using-query-strings">Downloading Multiple Files using Query Strings</ref>,
which we recommend after you have completed the introductory lessons in this series.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="2">
                <head>Suggested Readings</head>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Lutz, Mark. “Ch. 4: Introducing Python Object Types”, <emph>Learning
Python</emph> (O’Reilly, 1999).</item>
                </list>
                <div type="3">
                    <head>Code Syncing</head>
                    <p>To follow along with future lessons it is important that you have the
right files and programs in your "programming-historian" directory. At
the end of each lesson you can download the "programming-historian" zip
file to make sure you have the correct code.</p>
                    <list type="unordered">
                        <item>programming-historian-1 (<ref target="/assets/python-lessons1.zip">zip</ref>)</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
