<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="manipulating-strings-in-python" xml:base="manipulating-strings-in-python/manipulating-strings-in-python.xml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Manipulating Strings in Python</title>
                <author role="original_author">
                    <persName>William J. Turkel</persName>
                    <persName>Adam Crymble</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="reviewers">Jim Clifford</editor>
                <editor role="editors">Miriam Posner</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>Programming Historian</distributor>
                <idno type="doi">10.46430/phen0013</idno>
                <date type="published">07/17/2012</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital, in a markdown format. This lesson is original. Available translations are the following:<ref type="translations" target="#manipular-strings-python #manipuler-chaines-caracteres-python #manipular-cadenas-de-caracteres-en-python"/>
                </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p>This lesson is a brief introduction to string manipulation techniques in Python.</p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term xml:lang="en">python</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div type="2" n="1">
                <head>Lesson Goals</head>
                <p>This lesson is a brief introduction to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/String_(computer_science)">string</ref> manipulation techniques in
Python. Knowing how to manipulate strings plays a crucial role in most
text processing tasks. If you’d like to experiment with the following
lessons, you can write and execute short programs as we’ve been doing in previous lessons in the series,
or you can open up a Python shell / Terminal to try them out on the
command line.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="2" n="2">
                <head>Manipulating Python Strings</head>
                <p>If you have been exposed to another programming language before, you
might have learned that you need to <emph>declare</emph> or <emph>type</emph> variables before you
can store anything in them. This is not necessary when working with
strings in Python. We can create a string simply by putting content
wrapped with quotation marks into it with an equal sign (=):</p>
                <ab>
                    <code lang="language-python" xml:id="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_0" corresp="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_0.txt" rend="block"/>
                </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="2" n="3">
                <head>String Operators: Adding and Multiplying</head>
                <p>A string is a type of object, one that
consists of a series of characters. Python already knows how to deal
with a number of general-purpose and powerful representations, including
strings. One way to manipulate strings is by using <emph>string operators</emph>.
These operators are represented by symbols that you likely associate
with mathematics, such as +, -, *, /, and =. When used with strings,
they perform actions that are similar to, but not the same as, their
mathematical counterparts.</p>
                <div type="3" n="3.1">
                    <head>Concatenate</head>
                    <p>This term means to join strings together. The process is known as
<emph>concatenating</emph> strings and it is done using the plus (+) operator. Note
that you must be explicit about where you want blank spaces to occur by
placing them between single quotation marks also.</p>
                    <p>In this example, the string "message1" is given the content "hello
world".</p>
                    <ab>
                        <code lang="language-python" xml:id="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_1" corresp="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_1.txt" rend="block"/>
                    </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="3" n="3.2">
                    <head>Multiply</head>
                    <p>If you want multiple copies of a string, use the multiplication (*)
operator. In this example, string <emph>message2a</emph> is given the content
"hello" times three; string <emph>message 2b</emph> is given content "world"; then
we print both strings.</p>
                    <ab>
                        <code lang="language-python" xml:id="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_2" corresp="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_2.txt" rend="block"/>
                    </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="3" n="3.3">
                    <head>Append</head>
                    <p>What if you want to add material to the end of a string successively?
There is a special operator for that (+=).</p>
                    <ab>
                        <code lang="language-python" xml:id="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_3" corresp="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_3.txt" rend="block"/>
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="2" n="4">
                <head>String Methods: Finding, Changing</head>
                <p>In addition to operators, Python comes pre-installed with dozens of
string methods that allow you to do things to strings. Used alone or in
combination, these methods can do just about anything you can imagine to
strings. The good news is that you can reference a list of String
Methods on the <ref target="https://docs.python.org/2/library/stdtypes.html#string-methods">Python website</ref>, including information on how to use
each properly. To make sure that you’ve got a basic grasp of string
methods, what follows is a brief overview of some of the more commonly
used ones:</p>
                <div type="3" n="4.1">
                    <head>Length</head>
                    <p>You can determine the number of characters in a string using <code rend="inline">len</code>. Note
that the blank space counts as a separate character.</p>
                    <ab>
                        <code lang="language-python" xml:id="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_4" corresp="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_4.txt" rend="block"/>
                    </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="3" n="4.2">
                    <head>Find</head>
                    <p>You can search a string for a <emph>substring</emph> and your program will return the
starting index position of that substring. This is helpful for further
processing. Note that indexes are numbered from left to right and that
the count starts with position 0, not 1.</p>
                    <ab>
                        <code lang="language-python" xml:id="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_5" corresp="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_5.txt" rend="block"/>
                    </ab>
                    <p>If the substring is not present, the program will return a value of -1.</p>
                    <ab>
                        <code lang="language-python" xml:id="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_6" corresp="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_6.txt" rend="block"/>
                    </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="3" n="4.3">
                    <head>Lower Case</head>
                    <p>Sometimes it is useful to convert a string to lower case. For example,
if we standardize case it makes it easier for the computer to recognize
that "Sometimes" and "sometimes" are the same word.</p>
                    <ab>
                        <code lang="language-python" xml:id="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_7" corresp="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_7.txt" rend="block"/>
                    </ab>
                    <p>The opposite effect, raising characters to upper case, can be achieved
by changing <code rend="inline">.lower()</code> to <code rend="inline">.upper()</code>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="3" n="4.4">
                    <head>Replace</head>
                    <p>If you need to replace a substring throughout a string you can do so
with the <code rend="inline">replace</code> method.</p>
                    <ab>
                        <code lang="language-python" xml:id="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_8" corresp="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_8.txt" rend="block"/>
                    </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="3" n="4.5">
                    <head>Slice</head>
                    <p>If you want to <code rend="inline">slice</code> off unwanted parts of a string from the beginning
or end you can do so by creating a substring. The same kind of technique
also allows you to break a long string into more manageable components.</p>
                    <ab>
                        <code lang="language-python" xml:id="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_9" corresp="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_9.txt" rend="block"/>
                    </ab>
                    <p>You can substitute variables for the integers used in this example.</p>
                    <ab>
                        <code lang="language-python" xml:id="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_10" corresp="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_10.txt" rend="block"/>
                    </ab>
                    <p>This makes it much easier to use this method in conjunction with the
<code rend="inline">find</code> method as in the next example, which checks for the letter "d" in
the first six characters of "Hello World" and correctly tells us it is
not there (-1). This technique is much more useful in longer strings –
entire documents for example. Note that the absence of an integer before
the colon signifies we want to start at the beginning of the string. We
could use the same technique to tell the program to go all the way to
the end by putting no integer after the colon. And remember, index
positions start counting from 0 rather than 1.</p>
                    <ab>
                        <code lang="language-python" xml:id="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_11" corresp="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_11.txt" rend="block"/>
                    </ab>
                    <p>There are lots more, but the string methods above are a good start. Note
that in this last example, we are using square brackets instead of
parentheses. This difference in <emph>syntax</emph> signals an important distinction.
In Python, parentheses are usually used to <emph>pass an argument</emph> to a
function. So when we see something like</p>
                    <ab>
                        <code lang="language-python" xml:id="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_12" corresp="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_12.txt" rend="block"/>
                    </ab>
                    <p>it means pass the string <emph>message7</emph> to the function <code rend="inline">len</code> then send the
returned value of that function to the <code rend="inline">print</code> statement to be printed. If
a function can be called without an argument, you often have to include
a pair of empty parentheses after the function name anyway. We saw an
example of that, too:</p>
                    <ab>
                        <code lang="language-python" xml:id="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_13" corresp="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_13.txt" rend="block"/>
                    </ab>
                    <p>This statement tells Python to apply the <code rend="inline">lower</code> function to the string
<emph>message7</emph> and store the returned value in the string <emph>message7a</emph>.</p>
                    <p>The square brackets serve a different purpose. If you think of a string
as a sequence of characters, and you want to be able to access the
contents of the string by their location within the sequence, then you
need some way of giving Python a location within a sequence. That is
what the square brackets do: indicate a beginning and ending location
within a sequence as we saw when using the <code rend="inline">slice</code> method.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="2" n="5">
                <head>Escape Sequences</head>
                <p>What do you do when you need to include quotation marks within a string?
You don’t want the Python interpreter to get the wrong idea and end the
string when it comes across one of these characters. In Python, you can
put a backslash (\) in front of a quotation mark so that it doesn't
terminate the string. These are known as escape sequences.</p>
                <ab>
                    <code lang="language-python" xml:id="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_14" corresp="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_14.txt" rend="block"/>
                </ab>
                <ab>
                    <code lang="language-python" xml:id="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_15" corresp="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_15.txt" rend="block"/>
                </ab>
                <p>Two other escape sequences allow you to print tabs and newlines:</p>
                <ab>
                    <code lang="language-python" xml:id="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_16" corresp="code_manipulating-strings-in-python_16.txt" rend="block"/>
                </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="2" n="6">
                <head>Suggested Reading</head>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>
Lutz, <emph>Learning Python</emph>
                        <list type="unordered">
                            <item>Ch. 7: Strings</item>
                            <item>Ch. 8: Lists and Dictionaries</item>
                            <item>Ch. 10: Introducing Python Statements</item>
                            <item>Ch. 15: Function Basics</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="2" n="7">
                <head>Code Syncing</head>
                <p>To follow along with future lessons it is important that you have the
right files and programs in your programming-historian directory. At the
end of each chapter you can download the programming-historian zip file
to make sure you have the correct code. Note we have removed unneeded
files from earlier lessons. Your directory may contain more files and
that’s ok!</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>programming-historian-1 (<ref target="/assets/python-lessons1.zip">zip</ref>)</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
