<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="up-and-running-with-omeka" type="original">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Up and Running with Omeka.net</title>
                <author role="original_author">Miriam Posner</author>
                <editor role="editors">Adam Crymble</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>Programming Historian</distributor>
                <idno type="doi">10.46430/phen0060</idno>
                <date type="published">02/17/2016</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital, in a markdown format. This lesson is original. Available translations are the following:<ref type="translations" target="#demarrer-avec-omeka-classic #poniendo-omeka-a-funcionar #introducao-omeka-net"/>
                </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p>Omeka.net makes it easy to create websites that show off collections of items.</p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term xml:lang="en">website</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <p>
                <ref target="http://www.omeka.net">Omeka.net</ref> makes it easy to create websites that show off collections of items.</p>
            <div type="2">
                <head>Sign up for an Omeka account</head>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Sign up for a trial account</desc>
                    <graphic url="up-and-running-01.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Go to <ref target="http://www.omeka.net">www.omeka.net</ref> and click on <hi rend="bold">Sign Up</hi>. Choose the Trial plan. Fill in the sign-up form. Check your email for the link to activate your account.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="2">
                <head>Create your new Omeka site</head>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Omeka.net account page</desc>
                    <graphic url="up-and-running-02.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>After you've clicked on the link in your email, click on Add a Site.</p>
                <p>Fill in information about your site's URL, the title you want to use, and a description if you'd like. Click on <hi rend="bold">Add Your Site</hi>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="2">
                <head>You have a new Omeka site!</head>
                <figure>
                    <desc>View your site</desc>
                    <graphic url="up-and-running-03.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>To see what it looks like, click on <hi rend="bold">View Site</hi>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="2">
                <head>An empty Omeka site</head>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Public view</desc>
                    <graphic url="up-and-running-04.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>This is your empty Omeka site, waiting to be filled in. To get back to your dashboard, click the <hi rend="bold">Back</hi> button or enter <hi rend="bold">http://www.omeka.net/dashboard</hi>. This time, click on <hi rend="bold">Manage Site</hi>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="2">
                <head>Switch themes</head>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Theme settings page</desc>
                    <graphic url="up-and-running-05.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Omeka allows you to change the look of your public-facing site by switching themes. To do this, click on <hi rend="bold">Appearance</hi> (at the top right of your dashboard). Switch themes by selecting one of the options on the page. Press the green <hi rend="bold">Use this theme</hi> button to activate your new theme. Then visit your public site by clicking on the name of your site at the top left of the page.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="2">
                <head>You have a new theme!</head>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Public view with the new theme</desc>
                    <graphic url="up-and-running-06.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Once you've checked out your new theme, head back to your dashboard. You can switch back to your old theme, stick with this one, or select one of the other options.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="2">
                <head>Install some plugins</head>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Plugins page</desc>
                    <graphic url="up-and-running-07.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Your Omeka site comes with plugins, which offer some extra
functionality. We need to enable them. To do that, click on the
<hi rend="bold">Plugins</hi> menu item at the top right. On the following page, click the <hi rend="bold">Install</hi> button for <hi rend="bold">Exhibit Builder</hi> (leave the options as they are on the page that follows) and <hi rend="bold">Simple Pages</hi>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="2">
                <head>Add an item to your archive</head>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Add an item</desc>
                    <graphic url="up-and-running-08.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Click on <hi rend="bold">Items</hi> on the left-hand menu and then (naturally!) <hi rend="bold">Add an item.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="2">
                <head>Describe your new item</head>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Make your item Public using checkbox circled here</desc>
                    <graphic url="up-and-running-09.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Remember, <hi rend="bold">Dublin Core</hi> refers to the descriptive information you'll enter about your item. All of this information is optional, and you can't really do it wrong. But try to be consistent.</p>
                <p>Be sure to click the <hi rend="bold">Public</hi> checkbox so that your item is viewable by the general public. If you don't click that box, only people who are logged into your site will be able to see the item.</p>
                <p>To add multiple fields — for example, if you want to add multiple subjects for your item — use the green <hi rend="bold">Add input</hi> button to the left of the text boxes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="2">
                <head>A tricky question</head>
                <figure>
                    <desc>What is this?</desc>
                    <graphic url="up-and-running-10.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>I'm creating an item record for my dog, Bertie. But am I describing Bertie <emph>himself</emph> or a <emph>photograph</emph> of Bertie? If it's the former, the <hi rend="bold">Creator</hi> would be — well, I guess that depends on your religious outlook. If it's the latter, the creator would be Brad Wallace, who took the photo.</p>
                <p>The decision about whether you're describing the object or the representation of the object is up to you. But once you've decided, be consistent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="2">
                <head>Attach a file to your item record</head>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Adding files to an item</desc>
                    <graphic url="up-and-running-11.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Once you've finished adding Dublin Core metadata, you can attach a file to your item record by clicking <hi rend="bold">Files</hi> at the top of the Dublin Core form. (You don't have to click <hi rend="bold">Add Item</hi> before you do this; Omeka will automatically save your information.) You can add multiple files, but be aware that the Basic plan only comes with 500 MB of storage space.</p>
                <p>Once you've added a file or files, you can add <hi rend="bold">Tags</hi> by clicking on the button. You can also click on <hi rend="bold">Item Type Metadata</hi> to choose the kind of thing — person, place, animal, vegetable, mineral — your item is. If you don't see the appropriate item type for your item, don't worry. We can add a new item type later.</p>
                <p>When you're all done, click the green <hi rend="bold">Add Item</hi> button.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="2">
                <head>You have an item!</head>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Browse Items, Admin view</desc>
                    <graphic url="up-and-running-12.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>This list contains all the items you've added. If the item were not public, it would have (Private) after the title. To see what the page for your new item looks like, click on the name of the item.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="2">
                <head>This is not the public page for your item.</head>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Item show, admin view</desc>
                    <graphic url="up-and-running-13.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>It may look like it, but this page isn't what a non-logged-in user will see when she navigates to the page for your item. To see what a user would see, click on the blue <hi rend="bold">View Public Page</hi> button on the right. (Or you can edit the item by clicking on <hi rend="bold">Edit this item</hi> at the top right.)</p>
            </div>
            <div type="2">
                <head>This is the public page for your item</head>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Item show, public view</desc>
                    <graphic url="up-and-running-14.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>This is what a general user will see if she navigates to your page.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="2">
                <head>Create a collection</head>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Add a Collection</desc>
                    <graphic url="up-and-running-15.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>You can begin to bring order to your list of items by grouping them together in collections. To do this, return to your dashboard, click on the <hi rend="bold">Collections</hi> tab, and click on <hi rend="bold">Add a Collection</hi>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="2">
                <head>Enter information about your collection</head>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Add collection metadata</desc>
                    <graphic url="up-and-running-16.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>In Omeka, metadata is king! Enter some information about your new collection, and remember to click on the <hi rend="bold">Public</hi> button near the bottom of the page. Then save your collection.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="2">
                <head>Add items to your collection</head>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Click the item checkbox to batch edit</desc>
                    <graphic url="up-and-running-17.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>To fill up the collection you just created, click on the <hi rend="bold">Items</hi> tab. From your <hi rend="bold">Browse Items</hi> list, click the boxes of the items that belong in your new collection. Then click on the <hi rend="bold">Edit</hi> button.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="2">
                <head>Choose the collection</head>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Select a collection from the dropdown</desc>
                    <graphic url="up-and-running-18.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>On the <hi rend="bold">Batch Edit Items</hi> page, select the Collection you'd like to add your items to. (Also, take note of all the other things you can do on this page.)</p>
            </div>
            <div type="2">
                <head>Check out your new collection</head>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Browse collections, public view</desc>
                    <graphic url="up-and-running-19.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Return to your public site. If you click on the <hi rend="bold">Browse Collections</hi> tab on the public-facing site, you should now have a new collection containing the items you identified.</p>
                <p>Now that you've added some items and grouped them into a collection, take some time to play with your site. It's beginning to take shape now that you have both individual items and thematic units. But Omeka can do even more. We'll talk about that in the next lesson.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="2">
                <head>Further Resources</head>
                <p>The Omeka team has put together great resources on the software's <ref target="http://info.omeka.net">help pages</ref>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
