<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="georeferencing-qgis" type="original">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Georeferencing in QGIS 2.0</title>
                <author role="original_author">
                    <persName>Jim Clifford</persName>
                    <persName>Josh MacFadyen</persName>
                    <persName>Daniel Macfarlane</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="reviewers">
                    <persName>Finn Arne Jørgensen</persName>
                    <persName>Peter Webster</persName>
                    <persName>Abby Schreiber</persName>
                </editor>
                <editor role="editors">Adam Crymble</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>Programming Historian</distributor>
                <idno type="doi">10.46430/phen0027</idno>
                <date type="published">12/13/2013</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital, in a markdown format. This lesson is original. Available translations are the following:<ref type="translations" target="#georreferenciamento-qgis #georreferenciar-qgis"/>
                </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p>In this lesson, you will learn how to georeference historical maps so that they may be added to a GIS as a raster layer.</p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term xml:lang="en">mapping</term>
                    <term xml:lang="en">data-visualization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div type="2">
                <head>Lesson Goals</head>
                <p>In this lesson, you will learn how to georeference historical maps so
that they may be added to a GIS as a raster layer. Georeferencing is
required for anyone who wants to accurately digitize data found on a
paper map, and since historians work mostly in the realm of paper,
georeferencing is one of our most commonly used tools. The technique
uses a series of control points to give a two-dimensional object like a
paper map the real world coordinates it needs to align with the
three-dimensional features of the earth in GIS software (in <ref target="/lessons/googlemaps-googleearth">Intro to
Google Maps and Google Earth</ref> we saw an 'overlay' which is a Google
Earth shortcut version of georeferencing).</p>
                <p>Georeferencing a historical map requires a knowledge of both the
geography and the history of the place you are studying to ensure
accuracy. The built and natural landscapes change over time, and it is
important to confirm that the location of your control points — whether
they be houses, intersections, or even towns — have remained constant.
Entering control points in a GIS is easy, but behind the scenes,
georeferencing uses complex transformation and compression processes.
These are used to correct the distortions and inaccuracies found in many
historical maps and stretch the maps so that they fit geographic
coordinates. In cartography this is known as <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rubbersheeting">rubber-sheeting</ref> because
it treats the map as if it were made of rubber and the control points as
if they were tacks 'pinning' the historical document to a three
dimensional surface like the globe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="2">
                <head>Getting Started</head>
                <p>Before proceeding with georeferencing in Quantum GIS, we need to
activate the appropriate Plugins. On the toolbar go to Plugins -&gt;
Manage and Install Plugins</p>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Figure 1</desc>
                    <graphic url="geo110.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>A window titled Plugin Manager will open. Scroll down to Georeference
GDAL and check the box beside it, and click OK.</p>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Figure 2</desc>
                    <graphic url="geo210.png"/>
                </figure>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>At this point, you need to shut down and relaunch QGIS. For the
purposes of this example, and to keep things as simple as possible,
don't reload your existing project but instead start a new project.</item>
                    <item>Set up the <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spatial_reference_system">Coordinate Reference System</ref> (CRS) correctly (see
<ref target="/lessons/qgis-layers">Installing QGIS 2.0 and adding Layers</ref> for a reminder)</item>
                    <item>Save this new project (under File menu, select Save Project) and
call it 'georeferencing.'</item>
                    <item>Add the 'coastline_polygon' layer (see <ref target="/lessons/qgis-layers">Installing QGIS 2.0 and
adding Layers</ref> for a reminder)</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="2">
                <head>Open the Necessary GIS Layers</head>
                <p>For the Prince Edward Island case study, we are going to use the
township boundaries as control points because they were established in
1764 by Samuel Holland, they are identified on most maps of PEI, and
they have changed very minimally since then.</p>
                <p>
                    <emph>Download lot_township_polygon:</emph>
                </p>
                <p>This is the shapefile containing the modern vector layer we are going to
use to georeference the historical map. Note that townships were not
given names but rather a lot number in 1764, so they are usually
referred to as 'Lots' in PEI. Hence the file name
'lot_township_polygon'.</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Navigate to the link below in your web browser and download the file.</item>
                </list>
                <p>
                    <ref target="http://www.gov.pe.ca/gis/license_agreement.php3?name=lot_town&amp;file_format=SHP">http://www.gov.pe.ca/gis/license_agreement.php3?name=lot_town&amp;file_format=SHP</ref>
                </p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>After downloading the file called 'lot_township_polygon', move it
into a folder that you can find later and unzip the file. (Remember
to keep the files together as they are all required to open this
layer in your GIS)</item>
                </list>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Figure 3</desc>
                    <graphic url="geo310.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <emph>Add lot_township_polygon to QGIS:</emph>
                </p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>under Layer on the toolbar, choose Add Vector Layer (alternatively
the same icon you see next to 'Add Vector Layer' can also be
selected from the tool bar)</item>
                    <item>Click Browse. Navigate to your unzipped file and select the file
titled 'lot_township_polygon.shp'</item>
                    <item>Click Open</item>
                </list>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Figure 4</desc>
                    <graphic url="geo41.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>For more information on adding and visualizing layers see <ref target="/lessons/qgis-layers">Installing
QGIS 2.0 and adding Layers</ref>.</p>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Figure 5</desc>
                    <graphic url="geo51.png"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="2">
                <head>Open the Georeferencer Tool</head>
                <p>Georeferencer is now available under the Raster menu on the toolbar –
select it.</p>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Figure 6</desc>
                    <graphic url="geo61.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <emph>Add your historical map:</emph>
                </p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>In the resulting window, click on the Open Raster button on the top
left (which looks identical to the Add Raster layer).</item>
                </list>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Figure 7</desc>
                    <graphic url="geo71.png"/>
                </figure>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Find the file titled 'PEI_LakeMap1863.jpg' on your computer and
select Open (the file <ref target="https://geospatialhistorian.files.wordpress.com/2013/02/pei_lakemap1863.jpg">can be downloaded here</ref> or in its original
location at the <ref target="https://islandimagined.ca/islandora/object/imagined:208687">Island Imagined</ref> online map repository)</item>
                    <item>You will be prompted to define this layer's coordinate system. In
the Filter box search for '2291′, then in the box below select
'NAD83(CSRS98) / Prince Edward …'</item>
                </list>
                <p>The result will look like this:</p>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Figure 8</desc>
                    <graphic url="geo81.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <emph>Adding control points:</emph>
                </p>
                <p>Plan the locations you are going to use as control points in advance of
the steps that follow. It is much easier to navigate around the
historical map first, so get a good idea of the best points to use and
keep them in mind.</p>
                <p>Some tips for choosing control points:</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="bold">How many</hi> points do you need? Usually the more points you assign
the more accurate your georeferenced map will be. Two control points
will tell the GIS to scale and rotate the map to those two points,
but in order to truly rubber-sheet the historical document you need
to add more points.</item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="bold">Where</hi> should you put control points? Select areas as close as
possible to the four corners of your map so that these outer areas
do not get omitted in the rubber-sheeting.</item>
                    <item>Select additional control points close to your area of interest.
Everything in between the four corner control points should
georeference evenly, but if you are concerned about the accuracy of
one place in particular, make sure to select additional control
points in that area.</item>
                    <item>Select the middle of intersections and roads, because the edges of
roads changed a certain amount over time as road improvements were
made.</item>
                    <item>Check that your control points did not change location over time.
Roads were often re-routed, and even houses and other buildings were
moved, especially <ref target="http://books.google.ca/books?id=TqCNZYXWXAUC&amp;dq=tilting&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s">in Atlantic Canada</ref>!</item>
                </list>
                <p>
                    <emph>Add your first control point:</emph>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="bold">First</hi>, navigate to the location of your first control point on the
<hi rend="bold">historical map</hi>.</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>click on Zoom In Magnifying Glass on the window tool bar or use the
mouse roller wheel to zoom in</item>
                </list>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Figure 9</desc>
                    <graphic url="geo91.png"/>
                </figure>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>
                        <p>zoom in to a point which you can recognize on both your printed map
and your GIS</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Click on Add Point on toolbar</p>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Figure 10</desc>
                    <graphic url="geo101.png"/>
                </figure>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Click on the place in the printed map that you can locate in your
GIS (i.e. the control point). The Georeferencer window will now
minimize automatically. If it does not (some versions have a bug in
this plugin) manually minimize the window</item>
                    <item>Click on the place in the GIS which matches the control point</item>
                </list>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Figure 11</desc>
                    <graphic url="geo111.png"/>
                </figure>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>At this stage we identified a problem in lot boundaries. We planned
to use the location where the southern border of Lot 1 at the West
end of the Province contains a "dog leg" near the middle of the land
mass. However, it was clear that not all the dog legs on these lots
matched the historical map. It is possible that lot boundaries have
changed somewhat in the 250 years since they were established, so it
is best to choose the point you are most sure of. In this case the
dog leg between Lot 2 and Lot 3 was fine (see arrow). It was the
border of Lots 3 and 4 that has changed. The discrepancy at the
border of 1 and 2 shows that more control points are needed to
properly rubber-sheet this somewhat distorted 1863 map to the
Provincial GIS layer</item>
                </list>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Figure 12</desc>
                    <graphic url="geo121.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <emph>Add at least one more control point:</emph>
                </p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>return to the Georeferencer window and repeat the steps under '<emph>Add
your first control point</emph>' above, to add additional control points.</item>
                    <item>Add a point close to the opposite side of your printed map (the
further apart your control points are placed the more accurate the
georeferencing process) and another one near Charlottetown</item>
                    <item>return to the Georeferencer window. You should see three red dots on
the printed map, and three records in the GCP table at the bottom of
your window (outlined in red on the following image)</item>
                </list>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Figure 13</desc>
                    <graphic url="geo131.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <emph>Determine the transformation settings:</emph>
                </p>
                <p>Before you click Play and start the automated georeferencing process you
need to tell QGIS where to save the new file (this will be a raster
file), how it should interpret your control points, and how it should
compress the image.</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Click on the Transformation Settings button</item>
                </list>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Figure 14</desc>
                    <graphic url="geo141.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Most of these settings can be left as default: linear transformation
type, nearest neighbour resampling method, and LZW compression. (The
<ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World_file">world file</ref> is not necessary, unless you want to georeference the
same image again in another GIS or if someone else needs to georeference
the image and does not have access to your GIS data, coordinate
reference system, etc.) The target SRS is not important, but you could
use this feature to give the new raster a different reference system.</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Assign a folder for your new georeferenced raster file. <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tagged_Image_File_Format">Tif</ref> is
the default format for rasters georeferenced in QGIS.</item>
                    <item>Be aware that a Tif file is going to be much larger than your original map,
even with LZW compression, so make sure you have adequate space if you are
using a jump drive. (<emph>warning:</emph> the Tif file produced from this 6.8 Mb .jpg
will be <hi rend="bold">over 1GB</hi> once georeferenced. One way to manage the size of the
georeferenced raster file while maintaining a high enough resolution for
legibility is to crop out only the area needed for the map project. In this
case, a lower resolution option is also available from the <ref target="https://islandimagined.ca/islandora/object/imagined:208687">Island
Imagined</ref> online map repository.)</item>
                    <item>Leave the target resolution at the default</item>
                    <item>You can select 'Use 0 transparency when needed' to eliminate black
spaces around the edges of the map, but this is not necessary and
you can experiment as needed</item>
                    <item>Make sure 'Load in QGIS' is selected to save a step. This will
automatically add the new file to your GIS's Table of Contents so
that you don't have to go looking for the Tif file later</item>
                </list>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Figure 15</desc>
                    <graphic url="geo151.png"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="2">
                <head>Georeference!</head>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Click on the Play button on the toolbar (beside Add Raster) – this
begins the georeferencing process</item>
                </list>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Figure 16</desc>
                    <graphic url="geo161.png"/>
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Figure 17</desc>
                    <graphic url="geo171.png"/>
                </figure>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>A window will appear titled Define CRS: select 2291, click OK</item>
                </list>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Figure 18</desc>
                    <graphic url="geo181.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <emph>Explore your map:</emph>
                </p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Drag the new layer 'PEI_LakeMap1863_modified' down to the bottom
of your Table of Contents (i.e. below the 'lot_township_polygon'
layer</item>
                </list>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Figure 19</desc>
                    <graphic url="geo191.png"/>
                </figure>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Change the fill of the lot_township_polygon layer to 'no brush' by
Selecting the layer, clicking on Layer -&gt; Properties, and clicking
on Symbol Properties. Click OK</item>
                </list>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Figure 20</desc>
                    <graphic url="geo201.png"/>
                </figure>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Now you should see the modern GIS layer with the historical map in
behind</item>
                </list>
                <figure>
                    <desc>Figure 21</desc>
                    <graphic url="geo211.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Now that you have a newly georeferenced map in your GIS you can explore
the layer, adjust the transparency, contrast and brightness, and go back
through <ref target="/lessons/vector-layers-qgis">Creating New Vector Layers in QGIS</ref> to digitize some of the
historical information that you have created. For instance, this
georeferenced map of PEI shows the locations of all homes in 1863,
including the name of the head of household. By assigning points on the
map you can enter home locations and owner names and then analyze or
share that new geospatial layer as a shapefile.</p>
                <p>By digitizing line vectors such as roads or coastlines you can compare
the location of these features with other historical data, or simply
compare them visually with the lot_township_polygon layer in this GIS.</p>
                <p>In more advanced processes you can even drape this georeferenced image
over a DEM (digital elevation model) to give it a hillshade terrain or
3D effect and perform a 'fly-over' of PEI homes in the nineteenth
century.</p>
                <p>
                    <emph>This lesson is part of the <ref target="http://geospatialhistorian.wordpress.com/">Geospatial Historian</ref>.</emph>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
