<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="installing-python-modules-pip">
  <teiHeader>
 <fileDesc>
  <titleStmt>
   <title>Installing Python Modules with pip</title>
  <author role="original_author">Fred Gibbs</author><editor role="reviewers"><persName>Ben Hurwitz</persName><persName>Amanda Morton</persName></editor></titleStmt>
  <publicationStmt>
   <idno type="doi">10.46430/phen0029</idno><date type="published">05/06/2013</date><p>Lesson reviewed and published in Programming Historian.</p>
  </publicationStmt>
  <sourceDesc>
  <p>Born digital, in a markdown format. This lesson is original. Available translations are the following:<ref type="translations" target="#instalar-modulos-python-pip #instalacao-modulos-python-pip #installation-modules-python-pip"/></p></sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
 <profileDesc><abstract><p>There are many ways to install external python libraries; this tutorial explains one of the most common methods using pip.</p></abstract><textClass><keywords><term xml:lang="en">get-ready</term><term xml:lang="en">python</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <body>
      <div type="2"><head>Lesson Goals</head>
<p>This lesson shows you how to download and install Python modules. There
are many ways to install external modules, but for the purposes of this
lesson, we&#8217;re going to use a program called pip, easily installable on <ref target="https://pip.pypa.io/en/stable/">mac/linux</ref> and <ref target="https://sites.google.com/site/pydatalog/python/pip-for-windows">windows</ref>. As of Python 2.7.9 and newer, pip is installed by default. This tutorial will be helpful for anyone using older versions of Python (which are still quite common).</p>
</div>
      <div type="2"><head>Introducing Modules</head>
<p>One of the great things about using Python is the number of fantastic
code libraries that are widely and easily available that can save you a
lot of coding, or simply make a particular task (like creating a CSV
file, or scraping a webpage) much easier. When Googling for solutions to
problems, you&#8217;ll often find sample code that uses code libraries you
haven&#8217;t heard about before. Don&#8217;t let these scare you away! Once these
libraries are installed on your computer, you can use them by importing
them at the beginning of your code; you can import as many libraries as
you&#8217;d like, such as</p>
<ab><code xml:id="code_installing-python-modules-pip_0" corresp="code_installing-python-modules-pip_0.txt" lang="language-python" rend="block"/></ab>
<p>For new Python users, it can be a bit intimidating to download and
install external modules for the first time. There are many ways of
doing it (thus adding to the confusion); this lesson introduces one of
the easiest and most common ways of installing python modules.</p>
<p>The goal here is to install software on your computer that can
automatically download and install Python modules for us. We&#8217;re going to
use a program called <ref target="https://pip.pypa.io/en/stable/">pip</ref>.</p>
<p>Note: As of Python 3.4, pip will be included in the regular install.
There are many reasons why you might not have this version yet, and in
case you don&#8217;t, these instructions should help.</p>
</div>
      <div type="2"><head>Mac and Linux instructions</head>
<p>As per the pip documentation, we can download a python script to install
pip for us. Using a Mac or Linux, we can install pip via the command
line by using the <ref target="http://www.thegeekstuff.com/2012/04/curl-examples/">curl command</ref>, which downloads the pip installation
perl script.</p>
<ab><code xml:id="code_installing-python-modules-pip_1" corresp="code_installing-python-modules-pip_1.txt" lang="language-bash" rend="block"/></ab>
<p>once you&#8217;ve downloaded the get-pip.py file, you need to execute it with
the python interpreter. However, if you try to execute the script with
python like</p>
<ab><code xml:id="code_installing-python-modules-pip_2" corresp="code_installing-python-modules-pip_2.txt" lang="language-bash" rend="block"/></ab>
<p>the script will most likely fail because it won&#8217;t have permissions to
update certain directories on your filesystem that are by default set so
that random scripts cannot change important files and give you viruses.
In this case&#8212;and in all cases where you need to allow a script that you
trust to write to your system folders&#8212;you can use the <hi rend="bold">sudo</hi> command
(short for &#8220;Super User DO&#8221;) in front of the python command, like</p>
<ab><code xml:id="code_installing-python-modules-pip_3" corresp="code_installing-python-modules-pip_3.txt" lang="language-bash" rend="block"/></ab>
</div>
      <div type="2"><head>Windows Instructions</head>
<p>As with the above platforms, the easiest way to install pip is through
the use of a python program called get-pip.py, which you can download
<ref target="https://bootstrap.pypa.io/get-pip.py">here</ref>. When you open this link, you might be scared of the massive
jumble of code that awaits you. Please don&#8217;t be. Simply use your browser
to save this page under its default name, which is get-pip.py. It might
be a good idea to save this file in your python directory, so you know
where to find it.</p>
<p>Once you have saved this file, you need to run it, which can be done in
two ways. If you prefer using your python interpreter, just right-click
on the file get-pip.py and choose &#8220;open with&#8221; and then choose whatever
python interpreter you care to use.</p>
<p>If you prefer to install pip using the windows command line, navigate to
whatever directory you&#8217;ve placed python and get-pip.py. For this
example, we&#8217;ll assume this directory is python27, so we&#8217;ll use the
command C:\&gt;cd python27. Once you are in this directory, to install pip run the
command</p>
<ab><code xml:id="code_installing-python-modules-pip_4" corresp="code_installing-python-modules-pip_4.txt" lang="language-bash" rend="block"/></ab>
<p>If you want more information or help with a weird error message, check out the <ref target="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/4750806/how-to-install-pip-on-windows">StackOverflow
page</ref> that seems to be regularly updated.</p>
</div>
      <div type="2"><head>Installing Python Modules</head>
<p>Now that you have pip, it is easy to install python modules since it
does all the work for you. When you find a module that you want to use,
usually the documentation or installation instructions will include the
necessary pip command, such as</p>
<ab><code xml:id="code_installing-python-modules-pip_5" corresp="code_installing-python-modules-pip_5.txt" lang="language-bash" rend="block"/></ab>
<p>Remember, for the same reasons explained above (on Mac or Linux systems, but not Windows), you might need to run pip with sudo, like</p>
<ab><code xml:id="code_installing-python-modules-pip_6" corresp="code_installing-python-modules-pip_6.txt" lang="language-bash" rend="block"/></ab>
<p>Sometimes, especially on Windows, you may find it helpful to use the -m flag (to help python find the pip module), like</p>
<ab><code xml:id="code_installing-python-modules-pip_7" corresp="code_installing-python-modules-pip_7.txt" lang="language-bash" rend="block"/></ab>
<p>Happy installing!</p>
</div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
