<TEI xmlns="https://tei-c.org/ns/1-0/">
  <metadata>
  <title>Python Introduction and Installation</title>
  <layout>lesson</layout>
  <date>2012-07-17</date>
  <authors>William J. Turkel,Adam Crymble</authors>
  <reviewers>Jim Clifford,Amanda Morton</reviewers>
  <editors>Miriam Posner</editors>
  <difficulty>1</difficulty>
  <exclude_from_check>review-ticket</exclude_from_check>
  <activity>transforming</activity>
  <topics>python,get-ready</topics>
  <abstract>This first lesson in our section on dealing with Online Sources is designed to get you and your computer set up to start programming. We will focus on installing the relevant software – all free and reputable – and finally we will help you to get your toes wet with some simple programming that provides immediate results.</abstract>
  <redirect_from>/lessons/introduction-and-installation</redirect_from>
  <avatar_alt>A curled-up snake</avatar_alt>
  <doi>10.46430/phen0009</doi>
  <next>viewing-html-files</next>
  <series_total>15 lessons</series_total>
  <sequence>1</sequence>
</metadata>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <body>
      <div type="2" n="1"><head>Lesson Goals</head>
<p>This first lesson in our section on dealing with Online Sources is
designed to get you and your computer set up to start programming. We
will focus on installing the relevant software – all free and reputable
– and finally we will help you to get your toes wet with some simple
programming that provides immediate results.</p>
<p>In this opening module you will install the <link target="http://www.python.org/">Python programming
language</link>, the <link target="http://www.crummy.com/software/BeautifulSoup/">Beautiful Soup HTML/XML parser</link>, and a text editor.
Screencaps provided here come from <link target="http://www.activestate.com/komodo-edit">Komodo Edit</link>, but you can use any
text editor capable of working with Python. Here's a list of other
options: <link target="http://wiki.python.org/moin/PythonEditors/">Python Editors</link>. Once everything is installed, you will
write your first programs, "Hello World" in Python and HTML.</p>
</div>
      <div type="2" n="2"><head>the Python Programming Language</head>
<p>The programming language we will use in this series of lessons is Python,
a free, open source language. Unless otherwise noted, we will be using
<hi rend="bold">Python 3</hi> throughout. Version 2 is no longer officially supported,
but you might still find it used in older projects or lessons.
<link target="http://sebastianraschka.com/Articles/2014_python_2_3_key_diff.html">Python 3 has a few differences in formatting</link> (think grammar rules), so beware if you find examples online that still use Python 2. They might not run under current versions of Python.</p>
</div>
      <div type="2" n="3"><head>Backup Your Work!</head>
<p>Before you download or install any new software, it is crucial that you
make backups of your work. You should back up your whole computer at least
weekly, and preferably more frequently. It is also a good idea to make
off-site backups of your work, so that you don't lose everything if
something happens to your computer or to your home or office. Sites like
<link target="https://www.jungledisk.com/">Jungle Disk</link> and <link target="https://www.dropbox.com/home">Dropbox</link> provide easy-to-use and relatively
inexpensive online backup options.</p>
<div type="3" n="3.1"><head>Choose Your Operating System</head>
</div></div>
      <div type="2" n="4"><head>Step 1 – Install and Set Up Software</head>
<p>In order to work through the techniques in this website, you will need to
download and install some freely available software. We have provided
instructions for Mac, Windows and Linux. Once you have installed the
software for your operating system, move on to '<link target="/lessons/viewing-html-files">Viewing HTML Files</link>'.
If you run into trouble with our instructions or find something that
doesn't work on your platform, please let us know.</p>
<ul>
<li><link target="/lessons/mac-installation">Mac Python Installation</link></li>
<li><link target="/lessons/windows-installation">Windows Python Installation</link></li>
<li><link target="/lessons/linux-installation">Linux Python Installation</link></li>
</ul>
</div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
