<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="viewing-html-files">
  <teiHeader>
 <fileDesc>
  <titleStmt>
   <title>Understanding Web Pages and HTML</title>
  <author type="original_author"><persName>William J. Turkel</persName><persName>Adam Crymble</persName></author><editor type="reviewers"><persName>Jim Clifford</persName><persName>Amanda Morton</persName></editor><editor type="editors">Miriam Posner</editor></titleStmt>
  <publicationStmt>
   <idno type="doi">10.46430/phen0018</idno><date type="published">07/17/2012</date><p>Lesson reviewed and published in Programming Historian.</p>
  </publicationStmt>
  <sourceDesc>
  <p>Born digital, in a markdown format. This lesson is original. Available translations are the following:<ref type="translations" target="#nocoes-basicas-paginas-web-html #comprendre-les-pages-web #ver-archivos-html"/></p></sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
 <profileDesc><abstract><p>This lesson introduces you to HTML and the web pages it structures.</p></abstract><textClass><keyword xml:lang="en">python</keyword></textClass></profileDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <body>
      <div type="2"><head>"Hello World" in HTML</head>
</div>
      <div type="2"><head>Viewing HTML files</head>
<p>When you are working with online sources, much of the time you will be
using files that have been marked up with HTML (Hyper Text Markup
Language). Your browser already knows how to interpret HTML, which is
handy for human readers. Most browsers also let you see the HTML <emph>source code</emph>
for any page that you visit. The two images below show a typical web
page (from the <emph>Old Bailey Online</emph>) and the HTML source used to generate
that page, which you can see with the
<code type="inline">Tools -&gt; Web Developer -&gt; Page Source</code> menu item in Firefox.</p>
<p>When you're working in the browser, you typically don't want or need to
see the source for a web page. If you are writing a page of your own,
however, it can be very useful to see how other people accomplished a
particular effect. You will also want to study HTML source as you write
programs to manipulate web pages or automatically extract information
from them.</p>
<figure><desc>Old Bailey Online screenshot</desc><graphic url="obo.png"/></figure>
<figure><desc>HTML Source for Old Bailey Online Web Page</desc><graphic url="obo-page-source.png"/></figure>
<p>(To learn more about HTML, you may find it useful at this point to work
through the <link target="http://www.w3schools.com/html/default.asp">W3 Schools HTML tutorial</link>. Detailed knowledge of HTML
isn't immediately necessary to continue reading, but any time that you
spend learning HTML will be amply rewarded in your work as a digital
historian or digital humanist.)</p>
</div>
      <div type="2"><head>"Hello World" in HTML</head>
<p>HTML is what is known as a <emph>markup</emph> language. In other words, HTML is
text that has been "marked up" with <emph>tags</emph> that provide information for
the interpreter (which is often a web browser). Suppose you are
formatting a bibliographic entry and you want to indicate the title of a
work by italicizing it. In HTML you use <code type="inline">em</code> tags ("em" stands for
emphasis). So part of your HTML file might look like this</p>
<pre><code class="language-xml" xml:id="code_viewing-html-files_0" type="block" corresp="code_viewing-html-files_0.txt"/></pre>
<p>The simplest HTML file consists of tags which indicate the beginning and
end of the whole document, and tags which identify a <code type="inline">head</code> and a <code type="inline">body</code>
within that document. Information about the file usually goes into the
head, whereas information that will be displayed on the screen usually
goes into the body.</p>
<pre><code class="language-xml" xml:id="code_viewing-html-files_1" type="block" corresp="code_viewing-html-files_1.txt"/></pre>
<p>You can try creating some HTML code. In your text editor, create
a new file. Copy the code below into the editor. The first line tells
the browser what kind of file it is. The <code type="inline">html</code> tag has the text direction
set to <code type="inline">ltr</code> (left to right) and the <code type="inline">lang</code> (language) set to US English.
The <code type="inline">title</code> tag in the head of the HTML document contains material that is
usually displayed in the top bar of a window when the page is being
viewed, and in Firefox tabs.</p>
<pre><code class="language-xml" xml:id="code_viewing-html-files_2" type="block" corresp="code_viewing-html-files_2.txt"/></pre>
<p>Change both</p>
<pre><code class="language-xml" xml:id="code_viewing-html-files_3" type="block" corresp="code_viewing-html-files_3.txt"/></pre>
<p>and</p>
<pre><code class="language-xml" xml:id="code_viewing-html-files_4" type="block" corresp="code_viewing-html-files_4.txt"/></pre>
<p>to</p>
<pre><code class="language-xml" xml:id="code_viewing-html-files_5" type="block" corresp="code_viewing-html-files_5.txt"/></pre>
<p>Save the file to your <code type="inline">programming-historian</code> directory as
<code type="inline">hello-world.html</code>. Now go to Firefox and choose <code type="inline">File -&gt; New Tab</code> and
then <code type="inline">File -&gt; Open File</code>. Choose <code type="inline">hello-world.html</code>. Depending on your
text editor you may have a 'view page in browser' or 'open in browser'
option. Once you have opened the file, your message should appear in the
browser. Note the difference between opening an HTML file with a browser
like Firefox (which interprets it) and opening the same file with your
text editor (which does not).</p>
</div>
      <div type="2"><head>Suggested readings for learning HTML</head>
<ul>
<li><link target="http://www.w3schools.com/html/default.asp">W3 Schools HTML Tutorial</link></li>
<li><link target="http://www.w3schools.com/html/html5_intro.asp">W3 Schools HTML5 Tutorial</link></li>
</ul>
</div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
